<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A hand-kercheffe for a disconsolate soule, to wipe away his sinne, and to keep him from despaire, as though they had never been committed. / By Samuel Spinckes, minister of Gods word.</title>
            <author>Spinckes, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93682</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4981</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E633_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206473</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865630</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865630</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117878</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93682)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117878)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 97:E633[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A hand-kercheffe for a disconsolate soule, to wipe away his sinne, and to keep him from despaire, as though they had never been committed. / By Samuel Spinckes, minister of Gods word.</title>
                  <author>Spinckes, Samuel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Harper,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 3".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117878:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A HAND-KERCHEFFE FOR A DISCONSOLATE SOULE, To wipe away his Sinne, and to keep him from Deſpaire, as though they had never been committed.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Samuel Spinckes,</hi> Miniſter of Gods Word.</p>
            <q>
               <p>So apply the Promiſes of God unto thy Soule, that thou never deſpaire, but make him thine owne by Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, and hope thou in the Lord <hi>Jehovah,</hi> for by Hope we are ſaved,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.24.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Harper,</hi> 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:117878:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117878:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Much Honoured and truely Vertuous, THE LADY <hi>ANNE SCOTT,</hi> Late the Spouſeſſe of Sir <hi>EDWARD-SCOTT,</hi> of <hi>Scotts</hi> Hall, Knight and Baronet, the Mirrour of Piety; <hi>S. S.</hi> wiſheth all the Proſperous Events of Health and Happyneſſes, externall, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, and eternall.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Truth is moſt Divine, though croſſing hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſenſe, ſpoken by the Father of truth; but I will not heere ſtand blowing a Trumpet (as it were) either of your Worthineſſe, or my owne weakeneſſe: As for your Vertues and Almes-deeds, they ſhall and will follow you, when you ſhall be gathered to your Fathers, Revel. <hi>14.13.</hi> And for my imbecillity and weakneſſe, let the World laugh at it, I care not; onely my deſire is, that God may be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. I have made bold to preſent a Hand-kercheffe for a Diſconſolate Soule, under your name, aſſuring myſelfe (according to your wonted Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) of your loving acceptance; my deſire to doe good, and that to the
<pb facs="tcp:117878:3"/>poore and meaneſt ſoule, ſhall in part (as I hope) excuſe me in all: For we are all Debters (with that bleſſed Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. <hi>1.14.</hi>) both to the wiſe and unwiſe. And as it muſt and ought be our wiſdome chiefely to winne and gaine ſoules Prov. <hi>11.30.</hi> So it behooveth all Gods child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren to receive from us with meekeneſſe his Statutes and Judgements, Deut. <hi>4.6.</hi> I have heard you are as patient as <hi>Job,</hi> and like to <hi>Moſes</hi> milde, and altogether full of Vertue: In a word, although neither my perſon nor condition can any waies merrit at your Ladyſhips hands, yet the benigne aspect you alwaies afford to thoſe that labour in Gods Church hath thus far emboldned me, in all humility to crave that this my endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour may paſſe in Publique under your Ladyſhips name; which favour being happily obtained, the Worke and thing it ſelfe may of all ſorts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be the rather embraced: And ſo praying the Father of mercy to grant you much joy, health, and happineſſes terreſtriall, with a glorified life coeleſtiall, reſteth,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in all duty moſt bound,</hi> Samuel Spinckes.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117878:3"/>
            <head>A Hand-kercheffe for a diſconſolate Soule, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H! What ſhall I doe? what ſhall I ſay? Heerein obſerve the true Light of the World, and he will direct thee, Joh. 1.34. Even that Sonne of God, whom as yet the Diſciples knew not, neither did they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the myſteries of Redemption, the which are wrought by Chriſts humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation and exaltation: by the one (ſayth <hi>Aquinas</hi>) taking from us all evill, and by the other giving us all good: Oh why ſhould any then diſpayre of their ſalvation? ſeeing Chriſt came not for the juſt, but to call ſinners to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; for it is he that died for our ſinnes, and roſe againe for our juſtification, Rom. 4.25. Is it thus? Why then ſhould any deſpayre of everlaſting life? I dare ſay, it is abuſive much to thy Creator, to ſay that the joyes of the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven belong not unto thee: Wherfore take heed of thus abuſing or miſ-uſing of Gods mercies, and Chriſts merits; for Chriſt was betrayed, mocked, ſpitted on, ſcourged, and put to death, and all for our ſinnes: I ſay, truth it ſelfe was betrayed, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome it ſelfe mocked, glory it ſelfe ſpit upon, innocency it ſelfe ſcourged, life it ſelfe killed, and all for us, and our ſinnes, that we might not deſpayre. What ſhould a man doe to keep him from deſpayre? Confeſſe his ſinnes unto God, and that not once or only in generall, but often alſo, and that in particular; and be ſure to make ſatisfaction and reſtitution to thoſe thou haſt wronged: for the Law of God under the penalty of his curſe, requireth to reſtore whatſoever was wrongfully gained, Levit. 6.2.3. &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:117878:4"/>
            <p>Doe not thou then waver in thy fayth, for a wavering min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded man is unſtable in all his wayes, Jam. 1.8. For as the Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at the firſt, (ſayth <hi>Ponton</hi> on Luk. ch. 19.) drawes his pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture with a Coal roughly, and afterward with an accurate Pencil and Orient colours exactly, ſo the Holy Ghoſt in the Prophets and Old Teſtament ſhadowed Chriſts paſſion ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely, but in the latter and New Teſtament, points and ſets it downe (as it were) perſpicuouſly. The two Teſtaments are two pence, Luk. 10.35. bearing the ſame Kings Image, (ſayth <hi>Theophylact</hi> on Luke 10.) though not in the ſame ſtamp; for all things being now finiſhed and fulfilled that are written by the Prophets, of the ſame man, yet our Saviours picture engraven in the Goſpel, is more full and clear, then that which was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed in the Law: for now God hath ſhewed us the light of his countenance, Pſal. 67.1. Let us not therefore deſpayre for all the hub-bubs and garboiles, and warres, or diſcontents that are in the world, nay in this our Kingdome, but put ſure truſt and confidence in God, and wee ſhall ſee that the Lord in his good time will bring a period to thoſe diſtractions: Oh, I ſay, deſpayre not! but ſearch the Scriptures, for they are the way unto Chriſt, and Chriſt is the way to Heaven. <hi>Altiſſiodorenſis</hi> in his Golden Summe, ſayth, that Fayth, Hope, and Charity, are a created Trinity, reſembling the three Divine perſons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created. For the Son is begotten of the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt proceeds from both; ſo ſtedfaſt hope is bred of fayth, and love doth iſſue from them both. Whence obſerve, that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> cites often out of his Works againſt S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> that the foundation of Gods houſe in our ſoules, is faith, the walls hope, and the roofe charity. And the Prophet in a viſion ſaw the tranſgreſſour againſt the tranſgreſſour, and the deſtroyer againſt the deſtroyer. So the Schoolemen oppoſe the Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and their Champion <hi>Bellarmine</hi> fights againſt <hi>Bellarmine,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:117878:4"/>in the points of faith and charity: for if faith be the foundation of all other vertues in a Chriſtian, as himſelfe writes, in his firſt Booke of <hi>Romes</hi> Pontificals, and 10. chapter, then it is not as he diſputes in the firſt Booke of his Juſtification, and 4. chapter; that is wrought by charity: but contrariwiſe, charity doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe from faith. It is then an idle dreame to ſuppoſe that cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is incloſed in faith, as a Diamond is in a Ring; for Chriſt is the precious Pearle, ſaith <hi>Luther</hi> in Galla. 2.5. and Chriſt it is which gives life and luſtre to the Ring; for, the juſt live not by love, but by faith in the Lord Jeſus, Habak. 2.4. It is an improper ſpeech then (as ſome of our Divines obſerve, as Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Fulke,</hi> in Gal. 5.6.) to ſay that faith worketh by love, as the body by the ſoule, the matter by the forme; for the ſoule rather worketh by the body, than the body by the ſoule. The matter is paſſive, the forme active: whence know ye, that tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations and afflictions are the patrimony of good men and good women: therefore never diſpaire of mercy, for any vexation or trouble, nor have ſuch a thought in thee, as to think that Gods mercies are not for thee: I wiſh that all our Anabaptiſts and women-Preachers would have ſuch thoughts in them, then I am perſwaded it would make them more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to our Parliament, and to the truth of Gods holy word.</p>
            <p>Let no afflictions or troubles of this world (I ſay) daunt thee; for unto good men and women, afflictions and troubles in this life ſerve to admoniſh them of their infirmities, and the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of good people are made manifeſt unto the world by their troubles and croſſes of this life; wherefore, if thou beeſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in deſpaire, or beeſt caſt down upon thy bed of ſickneſſe, &amp;c. why then note, to thy comfort, as in a skirmiſh (as God grant it may be otherwiſe with this Kingdome, wherein there are now too many) in the warres: that when the conflict is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117878:5"/>once begun, then the courage of the Captaine, I ſay then, and not before, is his valour exerciſed and known; ſo when God doth call his children to any croſſe or calamity, then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins the battell, then their bleſſed patience and meek content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is made known and manifeſt; I ſay, then, or never, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that all goes by the hand of Gods providence, and holy Ordinance, in whom we live, move, and have our being, Acts 17.28. And know that no Phyſitian (I write this as a Hand-kercheffe to wipe away all teares from the eyes of ſuch as are mourners for ſin) can be more carefull for the health of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, then God is, and will be (if we be conſtant and confident in calling upon him by prayer, for mercy and favour in his Son, and our bleſſed Saviour Jeſus Chriſt) for the health of the ſoul, how bitter ſoever the potion and portion of our afflictions may ſeem to us; yet receiving it from him who meanes us ſo well, we ſhould not but receive it and them with patient ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, yea whatſoever his mercifull hands ſhall reach or lay up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon us, ſaying with holy and juſt Job, though he kill me, yet will I truſt in him, Job 13.15. My ſon, ſaith the Wiſe man, when thou commeſt to the ſervice of God, then prepare thy ſoule for temptations, and fears, and troubles, and ſhrink not away when thou art tryed; for, whom the Lord loveth, him he chaſteneth: as gold and ſilver are tried in the fire, ſo, I ſay, are our faith and patience tried in the furnace and fire of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: Sickneſſes, and afflictions are a means to purge out the droſſe of naturall corruption, which by reaſon of our ſins, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines within us.</p>
            <p>Afflictions being ſanctified (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi>) will bring us to a true fight of our ſinnes, and ſo to a hearty ſorrow for the ſame, and Affliction will teach Humility, even in the beſt of Gods Children, as <hi>Job, David, Paul;</hi> and a man that ſhould but read <hi>Johes</hi> Booke, <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalmes, and Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles, he could
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117878:5"/>not but wonder to thinke that ever they ſhould have any mirth at any time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If we put into the Ballance the afflictions of this life, they will be found of no weight, nor in any wiſe able to counterpoize the greatneſſe of the reward; for (as I ſayd before) tribulation is but a paſſion, and therefore ſmall is the force thereof, but glory is an action, and therefore powerfull, and encreaſeth every moment. This life paſſeth away ſwiftly, and ſoone vaniſheth, therefore deſpaire not, but ſtrive to make they election ſure, which may be done if thou canſt but believe, and ſo labour and endeavour for the glory to come, Eſay 64.4. which hath no end, and is full of ſweet comfort and happineſſe, more then heart can think, 1 Cor. 2.9. and endureth for ever and ever. Oh therefore, good Chriſtian ſoule, perſevere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly in a pure faith in Chriſt, and therin labour to finiſh your courſe, for great is your reward, which God hath promiſed, and Chriſt hath purchaſed, if thou canſt but believe in him. And mark this alſo for thy future and eternall comfort, that the life of a Chriſtian cannot be without ſin, nor temptations; for, I dare ſay, our profit and encreaſe in godlineſſe, is through temptations, (as St. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith) and his reaſon there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, for neither doth a man well know himſelfe, except he be tempted, neither can he be crowned except he overcome, neither can he overcome except he fight, neither can he fight except he have enemies and temptations, to encounter with. Whence again, note and obſerve, that God uſeth divers inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in tempting, troubling, and afflicting of his children; for ſometimes he uſeth the Devill, as he did with Job; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times wicked men he uſeth as a meanes, as the talſe witneſſes againſt our Saviour; and ſometimes he uſeth other creatures: but yet in all theſe there is a double comfort to Gods childe; firſt, that great and many are the troubles of the righteous: and then ſecondly, for their full comfort, the Lord will deliver
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117878:6"/>them out of all, Pſal. 34.19. the Prophet doth not ſay he hath, nor in the preſent, doth, but in the future, ſhall. Againe, if ye obſerve the ends of afflictions, therein alſo know, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we are afflicted, that we may be humbled, and the pride of our hearts abated; ſometimes to the end that we may not fix our love upon this world; ſometimes they are ſent to make us more zealous in good workes; and ſometimes they are ſent for this end, that pertaking with Chriſt in his ſufferings, we may alſo be glorified with him: and herein remember how the Lord tryed <hi>Abraham</hi> in offering up his Son, how he tryed <hi>Iſaac, Jacob,</hi> and all the Patriarchs with many and hard pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grinations, and think alſo how he tryed all the holy and godly Martyrs with ſcourges and torments, with fire and faggot, and thereby thinke, imagine and know, that the ſcourge of tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, ſtirreth up the drowſie, humbleth the proud, purgeth the penitent, and crowneth the innocent. Againe, know and underſtand, that the Lord afflicteth his children for theſe ends, that our faith thereby in the firſt place may be more pure, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and perfect, even as gold out of the furnace: Secondly, that we might the better know our ſelves, and our own frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and weakneſſe: Thirdly, in reſpect of others, that ſo we might be examples of patience and conſtancy unto them. Thus Chriſt proved the faith of <hi>Peter</hi> on the Sea, and at his Paſſion, and againe after his Reſurrection. And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, that through his perſecutions and bonds (I ſay that thereby) many of the brethren were imboldned, and did more frankly ſpeake the truth, Philip. 1.14. even thorow my bonds, ſaith he: and hence proceeded thoſe confident ſpeeches of the Chriſtians, and holy Martyrs, to their tyrants and perſecutors, ſaying, torment us, rack us, condemne us, breake us in pieces; yet for all this your malice, and iniquity, it's nothing to our hurt, but for our joy and comfort, it is nothing but the tryall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117878:6"/>of our innocency; wherfore ſeeng it is thus, Oh! therefore never deſpaire of Gods mercy, but with the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> count it exceeding joy when ye fall into divers temptations, knowing that the trying of your faith bringeth forth patience, &amp;c. Comfort (Oh comfort!) your ſelves in, and with theſe words: And know, that through many tribulations ye muſt enter into the Kingdome of God, Acts, 14.22.</p>
            <p>Oh man! thou art created, thou art healed, if by faith thou canſt ſee it; yea, thou art ſaved, if thou wilt perceive it: but which of all theſe are from thy ſelfe? I dare ſay not any of them; for thou couldſt not create thy ſelfe, when thou waſt not; thou couldſt not juſtifie thy ſelfe, when thou waſt a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and worſe then thou hadſt not beene; thou couldſt not raiſe thy ſelfe, when thou waſt dead, becauſe then thy ſtrength was, as if thou hadſt never been. When then is a mans free will in the ſtate of nature? ſeeing the Roman Church boaſts much of their free-will, where is our merit at the hand of God? Thoſe that are wiſe do conſider a three-fold operation, not offree-will to merit, (as the Roman Church teacheth) but of divine grace, and all theſe in man, but from God. The firſt is our Creation, the ſecond a Reformation, the third our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation and perfection to glory; and God I ſay is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of all theſe; for all our being, and well-being is from God the Father, in, and by Chriſt, and by the Bleſſed Spirit; and therefore to us humility, but to God onely belongs the glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But here ſome may reply, and ſay, ſurely I have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore felt (as I thought) the beginnings of Grace, and a new re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed life and converſation, by which I was perſwaded, that I was formed wholy to Chriſt my Redeemer: thus I was once perſwaded, yet now I find that I am ſubject to manifold temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and ſometimes overcome to fall into grievous ſinnes,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117878:7"/>which wound my conſcience; yea, I ſee a decay of grace in my ſelfe, I find a weakneſſe of faith, and a kind of deadneſſe in my ſoul, ſo that I delight not in the Law of God, as I ſhould, nor do I feele that aſſurance of the favour of God, and of my ſalvation, as I deſire; and therefore I feare, that the faith that I had was but faigned, and my holineſſe but in ſhew, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now I doubt that my eſtate and condition is fearefull, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and miſerable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Respon.</hi> This is a very large Objection, and hath many parts, but I will anſwere them all with what brevity I may, and firſt, for the Concluſion; who told thee that thou waſt in Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour? It may be thou wilt reply, it was, and is, thine owne conſcience, ſeeing thy decay in faith, in holineſſe, and the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of thy ſinnes too heavy for thee to beare, and therefore this pronounceth the curſe againſt thee, becauſe thou haſt not continued in all things that are written in Gods Law to doe them, Levit. 27.26. and becauſe thou haſt not that meaſure of grace which ſhould be in a Chriſtian, in ſuch an one as is in Gods favour; but who is this that thus perſwades thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to theſe doubtings? Shall I tell thee who it is? Why then know, it may be either God, or Sathan: Firſt, I ſay, it may be it is God, which if it be ſo, then know certainely, it is for thy good, and that God for a time leaves thee to thy ſelfe, and ſo ſuffers thoſe doubtings to be in thee; it may be it is for ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſinne, for which, as yet thou art not fully and abſolutely humbled, nor haſt not truely as yet repented thee thereof, and in ſuch a caſe then God doth it to worke humiliation in thee, that ſo thou mayſt be ſaved; or it may be it is to keepe thee from ſecurity, and to make thee ſo much the more to abhorre and feare ſinne, or to prevent ſpir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tuall pride in thee, to trie thy faith, patience, conſtancy, and true truſt in his promiſes; or elſe it is to move thee to eſteeme better of Gods ſervice, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117878:7"/>of all ſpirituall graces heereafter; or it may be it is to teach thee to flie by earneſt prayer unto Chriſt thy Saviour, and to mplore mercy at his hands, with the renewing of his ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all grace in thee, becauſe in Chriſt God is well pleaſed, and in him thou mayſt have, and finde mercy, yea even in the depth of all thy miſery; but I ſay, If it be God that brings all theſe doubtings into thy mind, then I dare ſay that it is a ſure argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to confirme thy faith, and aſcertaine thee that thou art Gods child, and that ſo his mercy ſhall imbrace thee on every ſide; and thus it is, I ſay that God tempteth, and it is then for thy good, if God do thus tempt thee.</p>
            <p>But not ſo with Sathan, for if Sathan tempt and perſwade thee to theſe doubtings, then he doth it to worke deſpaire in thy ſoule, and ſo to procure thy utter ruine and deſtruction; and therefore believe him not, but reſiſt his temptations at the very firſt, as the Apoſtle adviſeth 1 Pet. 5.9. and ſo prevent all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions; for, according to the Proverb, <hi>Give the Devill an Inch, and he will take an Ell:</hi> and take heed of ſolitarineſſe, and of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too much alone, but uſe company; if thou beeſt naturally given to mellancholly, then I ſay, uſe merry company, for thy recreation, but take heed of being alone, leſt Sathan may deale with thee as he did with Eve, when ſhe was alone, for then it was that he tempted her, Gen. 3.2, 3.</p>
            <p>Therefore I ſay, be circumſpect, and give no credit to Sathan when he ſhall perſwade thee to any evill motion or action, for he is a Liar, John 8.48. and he is thy enemy, yea, thy accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing enemy, and one that ſeeketh to devoure thee, 1 Pet. 5.8. and why ſhouldſt thou believe a liar, or any way credit thine adverſary, rather than the ſweete promiſes of the Father of mercy? how full the holy Scriptures are of the ſweet promiſes of mercy! let a man ſearch and he ſhall finde, as in Ezek. 18.27. he that doth righteouſneſſe, not he that ſaith, but he that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117878:8"/>doth, ſhall ſave his ſoule alive: and come unto me all ye that are weary, &amp;c. Mat. 11.28. and for this, read Job 13, 14, 15. with others: And therefore hold this for a ground; although thou mayſt be ſubject to doubtings, yet by, and with Gods aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, with holy Job, thou wilt never deſpaire, but pray ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly and without ceaſing for the gift of perſevering: And thus ſhalt thou find comfort in the latter end: and thus thou mayſt perceive then how thou mayſt obtaine the joyes of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and not to deſpayre. Againe, peradventure thou wilt ſay, I know there is much joy and happineſſe in Heaven pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for the elect, but what's that to me? For I ſhall have no ſhare thereof, I know it, by reaſon I am ſo ſubject to ſo many temptations, and entiſed often to grievous ſinnes, ſometimes with the Atheiſt, to thinke that there is no God, as alſo to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the providence and power of God, harping that all things happen by fortune and chance; ſometimes againe I am ready to deny Chriſt, the ſecond Perſon in the Holy and Sacred Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and ſometimes I am ready to lay violent hands upon my ſelfe, and thus to ſinne ſometimes againſt the firſt Table, and ſometimes againſt the ſecond: Yea, and although I pray to be free there from, yet I cannot; well, I ſhall tell thee the reaſon of this, Sathan is thy utter enemy, and for that cauſe, both he and the world, and the fleſh, will not leave aſſaulting thee, and therefore it is that thou doubteſt, and thinkeſt withall, that thou oughteſt not to apply the favour and mercy of God unto thy ſelfe. Unto theſe I fully anſwer: That theſe tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and corruptions may ſometimes be found even in the beſt of Gods children, (yea, in thoſe upon whom God hath beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an excellent meaſure of grace) the which either ariſeth from the corruptions of their owne natures, from which they are not fully purged, and in which there are the ſeeds of all theſe ſinnes of Atheiſme, Infidelity, and the like, or elſe from
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117878:8"/>the temptations of Sathan, from which they neyther are nor can be free, ſo long as they live in this vale of miſery. <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle was often buffetted with Sathans temptations. <hi>Peter</hi> had a ſhrewd fall, when hee denied his Maſter: <hi>Noah, Lot,</hi> and ſaythfull <hi>Abraham,</hi> they had their reſurrections from ſinns, as I may ſay, and <hi>David,</hi> (though a man according to Gods own heart, Acts 13.22.) yet he was conſtrained to pray, as Pſa. 51.10. for to have a new heart created in him, &amp;c. And how terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble were Jobs temptations, as we may read, Job 6.4. if theſe men were not free, then how canſt thou looke to be priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged? But to ſatisfie thee further herein, know that thou art yet a member of the Church militant, and ſo long as thou art ſo, thou art, and ſhalt be ſubject to theſe fightings and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings againſt the temptations of Sathan continually, nor canſt thou be free from theſe, till thou be a member of the Church triumphant, which ſhall be in the world to come; for, firſt, our regeneration is not fully perfected in this life, and therfore the ſeeds of ſin and corruption remaining, there is a feare and doubting even in Gods deareſt children, yea, and ſometimes a kind of deſpaire too; Oh! but in this know for thy comfort, that Chriſt (thine and our ſweet Saviour) hath felt the terrors of Gods wrath and abſence, that ſo his faithfull ones might bee delivered from it; yet know this alſo, that there will bee a combate in thee, (if thou beeſt Gods) even betweene the fleſh and the ſpirit. Againe, Sathan is a perpetuall enemy, and hee will never leave off to ſeek thy deſtruction: howſoever, thou mayſt get the victory, and be at peace for a time, (when upon true repentance thou art reconciled unto God) yet thy ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies will adventure againe, and thou ſhalt bee ſure of many battels and skirmiſhes with them, before thou canſt paſſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the wilderneſſe of this world, to the Canaan of Heaven. But yet take this againe for thy comfort, that temptations are
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117878:9"/>ſure ſignes, that they that are troubled and poſſeſſed therewith are the deare children of God.</p>
            <p>And temptations are profitable for a Chriſtian, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Saint James ſaith, my deare brethren, count it exceeding joy when ye fall into divers temptations, knowing that, &amp;c. Ja. 1.2.3. &amp;c. nay, our Saviour himſelfe was tempted, and that to grievous ſins too, as ye may ſee, Mat. 4. as to Idolatry, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt of Gods providence, and to doubt whether he were the Sonne of God or not; nay, hee was alſo tempted to pride and vain-glory, yea to lay violent hands upon himſelfe, and ſo to be the cauſe of his owne death; and when the Devill left him, ſaith the text, Luk. 4.13. it was but for a ſeaſon. St. Paul was an excellent Chriſtian, and the deare child of God, and yet he could not be free from aſſaults, Rom. 7.23. for he had the ſeeds of ſin in him, and he had a Law in his members, rebelling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law of his minde, and often leading him into the Law of ſin; for hee had inward enemies, and hee was not free from outward; for he had the meſſenger of Sathan ſent to buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet him 2 Cor. 12.7, 8. that is, Sathan ſtill aſſaulted him with one temptation or other to move him forward and to provoke him to ſinne. And St. Paul prayed thrice; that is, often and earneſtly, to be freed therefrom, and that he might have no more of theſe aſſaults and troubles, and yet hee could not bee free; and why did not God give and grant his deſire and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt? if he would have given this freedome to any, then why not to Saint Paul? I anſwer, the ſtate of the Apoſtle required it (being a member of the Church militant) that he ſhould not be free; leaſt he might grow ſecure, leave off fighting, and ſo ceaſe to be a Souldier, which we muſt not do in this life, for we then breake our vowes and oaths made by our Sureties or Parents in our Baptiſms: wherfore we muſt, I ſay, fight man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully under Chriſts Croſſe and Banner againſt the three deadly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117878:9"/>enemies of the ſoule, the world, the Devill, and the fleſh, and be faithfull unto death, and then thou ſhalt have a crown of life, Revel. 2.10.</p>
            <p>It is the property of the Devill (ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard</hi>) to ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt evill motions, but it is our parts and duties not to conſent unto them; for, as often as we reſiſt, ſo often we overcome the Devill, and we thereby doe honour our God, who viſiteth us, that we ſhould fight, who helpeth us that we may over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and who ſtrengtheneth us that we faint not in our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate; to be tempted by Sathan, is Sathans ſinne, not thine, but to yield and conſent to his temptations, is ſinne in thee: And know this, that ſeeing our Saviour (as I ſhewed you a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) was ſo tempted to ſuch grievous temptations, therefore let none thinke to be free; but yet comfort thy ſelfe with this, that God (who is thy loving Father in Chriſt) hath the Devill in chaines; and as he ſtayeth the waves of the Sea at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, Job 38.8. So he holdeth Sathan (as it were) with bit and bridle, that he can tempt thee no otherwiſe, nor any longer, then God ſees for thy good, as is evident by the example of <hi>Job,</hi> Job 1.12. And if the children of God be tempted and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by any aſſault, yet upon true repentance and comming unto Chriſt, we have an Advocate with the Father, even Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt the righteous, and he is the propitiation for our ſins, 1. John 2.1. and in the firſt Epiſtle John 1.8.9. If we ſay that we have no ſinne, we deceive our ſelves, and the truth is not in us; but if we acknowledge our ſinnes, then he is fathfull (according to his promiſe) to forgive us our ſinnes, and to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>We muſt not therefore conclude and ſay, that becauſe we are ſubject to temptations, and becauſe the ſword is ſo predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant in our Kingdome, or becauſe the ſeeds of ſinnes are ſtill in us, and the corruptions of our natures are not fully purged,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117878:10"/>that therefore we are out of the favour of God; and firſt for the ſword ſo raigning in the Land, we muſt confeſſe it is for the ſinnes of the Land, which if once that cauſe were but remove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then the effect would ceaſe: What, wilt thou ſay that for theſe thou art out of Gods favour? Well then note againe, that theſe may be, and often are to be found even in Gods dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Saints; but heerein we may pray unto God for helpe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is the Lord of peace, who giveth peace unto his child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren; caſt thy care therefore upon God, the authour and fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher of thy faith, 1. Pet. 1.2. and uſe an endeavour by ſtrive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and labouring to reſiſt theſe temptations, and endure the combate with patience, having an eye to our Captaine, Chriſt Jeſus, who is the authour and finiſher of our faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Heb. 12.1.2. and know that God freely accepts us as righteous, not for any merrits of ours, but for the merrits of his deare Sonne, in whom onely he is well pleaſed, 2. Pet. 1.17. And alſo know, that whenſoever thou art in any temptation or doubtings to trouble thy ſoule, remember then, I ſay, that thy eſtate in this life, is like <hi>Peter</hi> on the water, whoſe faith at firſt was ſo ſtrong, that at the call of Chriſt, he came boldly to him on the waters without doubtings, but when he ſaw the waves comming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, then he preſently doubteth, and feareth drowning, and begins to ſinke, and finding himſelfe unable to ſave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, he flyeth to Chriſt, and prayeth earneſtly unto him for helpe; ſaying, Maſter, ſave me, I periſh: And then Chriſt giveth him his hand, and bringing him into the Ship, ſaveth him from drowning: And in like maner it is with a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an; for, at firſt, when Chriſt called him to faith and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, being perſwaded by the Spirit to believe, then he comes boldly unto Chriſt, being moved by the excellency of Chriſts merrits, and the free promiſes of grace and mercy in him; but when once he comes to ſee his owne unthankfulneſſe, and the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117878:10"/>weakeneſſe of his faith and obedience, and the unbeliefe and wants of ſanctification in him; then (the waves of Sathans temptations and corruptions of his own nature aſſaulting him) feares and doubtings ſeize upon him; and he is ready to ſinke downe into the ſea of diſpaire for want of faith. I ſay, if this be thy eſtate and thy caſe, as peradventure it may? What then muſt thou doe heerein? Onely this, confeſſe and acknowledge thine owne weakeneſſe and inſufficiency, and with <hi>Peter</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ready to ſinke) flie unto Chriſt, and pray unto him for comfort, who is the authour and fountayne of life and peace; for if any be afflicted, let him pray, ſayth Saint James, 5.13. And my houſe ſhall be called the houſe of prayer, ſaith our bleſſed Saviour, Mat. 21.13. But where is Gods houſe once called the houſe of preaching? neither yet in all Gods word, I am ſure, from the beginning of Geneſis to the end of the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, we doe not read of one quarter of the Miracles and Wonders that have been done by preaching, as have been by prayer; and the Apoſtle willeth us to prove and to examine our owne ſelves, not any man another, but himſelfe, 2. Cor. 13.5. And was or is that by preaching, and not rather by prayer? and pray continually, 1. Theſ. 5.17. And I dare ſay, that in any doubtings, troubles, and afflictions whatſoever that thou mayeſt be in, prayer may be the meanes to beget faith in thee to believe, and thou thereby mayeſt be ſaved and recovered, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But againe, if thou at any time doubteſt, becauſe of thy imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in any of thy aſſaults, and becauſe thou art not fully (as thou mayeſt imagine) regenerated: Know then, as I ſaid before, that Chriſt is thy perfection, and that God ſo behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thee in him, as that thou canſt not totally fall: For if we looke upon our ſelves, why then when we have done all that we can, yet alaſſe! wee muſt needes be conſtrayned to ſay, that we are but unprofitable ſervants, Luke 17.10. And for peace
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117878:11"/>in our ſelves, we cannot finde any. So that as <hi>Noahs</hi> Dove was conſtrayned to flie backe againe into the Arke, before ſhee could finde whereon to reſt the ſole of her foot, Gen. 8.9. So are we conſtrayned to flie to Chriſt, before we can finde reſt to our ſoules. As the Iſraelites being ſtung with the fiery Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, preſently looking upon the brazen Serpent, were healed and cured, Num. 21.9. So whenſoever thou art wounded by ſinne, or moved to doubtings, by thine owne weakneſſe, or Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans temptations, then ſlie preſently to Chriſt, and behold him by the eye of fayth, how he was crucified, how hee ſhed his moſt precious bloud, how he died and roſe againe, how he ſits at the right hand of his and our Father, and makes inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, and all for the purchaſe of thy peace, and for the joy and comfort of as many as thus beleeve of him: Oh now! with this perſwaſion, I ſay, poſſeſſe thy ſoule in patience and hope, that thou ſhalt one day enjoy that inheritance of the Saints, where is freedome from all theſe feares and doubtings, which Chriſt hath bought and purchaſed for thee. O deſpayre not then! for Chriſt, I ſay, hath purchaſed and bought eternall life, and everlaſting joyes for thee; and not by or with thy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, but by and with the price of his owne moſt pretious bloud, this hope will not make aſhamed, Rom. 5.5. Yea, by and with this hope, thou art and ſhalt bee ſaved, Rom. 8.24. Doe not therefore conclude and ſay, that the joyes of heaven belong not to thee; this is to abuſe that ſweet and loving mercy of God; for, as you have heard but even a little before, from the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> wee are ſaved by hope, oh then thinke not thy ſelfe to be out of the favour of God, or that the joyes or happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of Gods holy Kingdome, belongs not or appertaines not to thee, becauſe thou art not yet free from ſinne, and Sathans temptations, but comfort thy ſelf in hope, that as Chriſts prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for <hi>Peter</hi> was heard, that (though hee fayled in fayth, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117878:11"/>that for a time, yet) he could not faile and fall totally and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, and ſo alſo, I dare ſay, it is hard for thee; for, Chriſt hath prayed for thee as earneſtly and as effectually as he did for him, yea, and for all that ſhall but believe in him, John 17.20. and therefore, Job 19.2. as <hi>Job</hi> in the midſt of his miſery, did comfort himſelfe with this meditation, that his Redeemer lived: So doe thou comfort thy ſelfe in Chriſt, that one drop of his blood is of efficacy, vertue, and power, to procure par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for all thy ſinnes; yea, and though all the ſinnes of all the whole world were thine. And therefore waite with patience, and be content with Gods anſwer to Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 2. Cor. 12.9. My grace is ſufficient for thee, and my ſtrength and power ſhall be made manifeſt in thy weakeneſſe: and know, that it is not for thy merits, but for the merits and worthineſſe of Chriſt, that God freely accepts us.</p>
            <p>And this is the very promiſe of God to thoſe who are once his, on whom he hath once beſtowed thoſe graces of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt, of fayth, of repentance, of regeneration, and newneſſe of life, (which thou canſt not deny, I thinke, but at ſometime to have beene in ſome meaſure in thee) though hee ſuffers thee to fall into divers great and grievous temptations, (yea, temptations of a very high nature) yet hee will lay no more upon thee (or them) then he will make thee and them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to beare, 1. Cor. 10.23. And though he ſuffer to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come for a time, yet will he make a way to eſcape, and will give grace of fayth and repentance, by which they may bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled and re-aſſured of the love of our heavenly Father. Doubt not then to apply the promiſes of God in particular un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy ſelfe, upon repentance and comming unto Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no kinde of ſinne, which thou canſt commit, but the mercies of God in Chriſt are farre greater. For that ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt, thou canſt not commit, which is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117878:12"/>not any tranſgreſſion of the Morrall Law, eyther in generall or in particular, eyther of ignorance, or of infirmity, or a ſin com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted wilfully, or preſumptuouſly, and againſt a mans owne conſcience, (though theſe be grievous ſinnes;) but it is an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall and finall Apoſtacie or falling away from Chriſt; I ſay, it is a voluntary renouncing of the knowledge or known truth of the Goſpel, and a rebellious proceeding from the hatred of it, being joyned with a tyrannicall, ſophiſticall, and hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call oppugnation of the ſame; when a man that hath beene en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned with a true knowledge of Chriſt, and is convinced in his conſcience of the truth of it, by the bleſſed Spirit, and hath taſted of the good word of God, Heb. 6.5. and of the powers of the world to come, (but it is only a taſte, for they that doe feede of theſe graces ſpiritually, and doe digeſt them, and are nouriſhed by them to newneſſe of life; I dare ſay; God will never ſuffer them to fall into this ſinne) when ſuch an one, I ſay, ſhall afterwards univerſally, and with a full conſent, fall from the truth, deny Chriſt, perſecute him (and though it be but in his members) with reproaches, deſpiſings, and taunts, and ſo diſdaine the ſacrifice of his death and paſſion, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing thus without repentance unto the end, this is the ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt. Thus did <hi>Julian,</hi> and other Apoſtats ſinne, and of theſe are that of the Apoſtle to be underſtood in Heb. 6.6.7.8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But to thy comfort whoſoever thou art, that art troubled with doubtings, and ſo feares that heaven and the joyes thereof belong not unto thee: This ſinne, I ſay, thou canſt not fall into (being firſt ingrafted into Chriſt by fayth;) and for all other ſinnes be they never ſo grievous, yet remiſſion is promiſed, upon fayth and repentance, and that freely, not for the merit of thy faith or repentance, but for the love and merits of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Why then ſhouldſt thou not apply the generall promiſes of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117878:12"/>grace unto thy ſelfe in particular? Come unto me (ſayth our bleſſed Saviour, Matt. 11.28.) all that are weary and heavy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and I will refreſh you. This promiſe is generall. But this thy owne conſcience will tell thee, that thou art weary and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den heavily with the burthen of thy ſinnes, and therefore thou mayeſt well conclude, that comming unto Chriſt, the promiſe of mercy belongs to thee: Whoſoever ſhall believe and be baptized, ſhall be ſaved, Mar. 16.16. this is a generall promiſe alſo. But thy owne conſcience will tell thee, that thou art Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptized, and that without our new fangled re-baptizings, and that thou beleeveſt (though it may be that thy faith is but weak but like a graine of muſtard ſeed, that is very ſmall, Matth. 7.20.) yet if thou canſt but ſay with the man in the Goſpel, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, Lord helpe my unbeleefe, Mar. 9.24. If thou canſt but touch the hemme of Chriſts garment with the finger of fayth, (if thy hand of fayth, by which thou mayſt lay faſt hold of him be wanting) yet by this touch of Chriſt, even but with the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of fayth, the vertue of Chriſt may flow foorth ſufficiently to ſtop the bloudy iſſue of thy ſinnes, and to cure the maladies of thy ſoule, and with this thou mayſt truely apply the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of grace unto thy ſoule. Well then! as you have ſeen, ſince thou art and muſt be a Soldier whileſt thou liveſt in the Camp, or Field of the Church; faint not at the ſight of thine enemies, though they be many and terrible, but comfort thy ſelfe with this, that (as <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſayd to his ſervant in the 2. Kin. 6.16.) there are more with thee then with them, yea, and though thou bee weake, yet the ſtronger part is on thy ſide; for thou haſt God thy friend, to ſend thee more ayd of grace, (if at any time thou art decayd in thy ſtrength) thou haſt Chriſt a Conqueror, thy Captaine, under whoſe Banner thou doeſt fight, thy friend; and thou haſt the bleſſed Spirit to encourage thee; and though he may leave off to ſhew his favourable preſence for a time,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117878:13"/>yet will he not bee long abſent from thee. Though for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he hide his face, yet with everlaſting kindneſſe will he have compaſſion on thee, Eſay 54.7.8. In a word, thou haſt, being in Chriſt, Myriads of Angels to accompany thee, and the prayers of the Saints, of the whole Church; yea, I ſay, and of Chriſt himſelfe, at the right hand of his and our Father; like the ſhouting of the Iſraelites, to make the walles of Jericho, the ſtrength of their enemies to fayle, Joſ. 6.20. And therfore faile nor, but there goe on, I adviſe thee, with fayth and conſtancy to endure the combat; and faint nor, though thou haſt many loſſes of grace, many wounds by ſinnes, and by thy ſpirituall enemies, for Chriſt being thy Captaine, thou ſhalt certainely prove a Conqueror in the end.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding all this, thou findeſt that thou art una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to apply the promiſes of mercy and free grace unto thy ſelf, or to doe it ſo weakely, that feare is not altogether removed out of the heart: Then as in the ſickneſſe of thy body, thou art ready to ſeeke and to ſend to the Phyſitian for health of thy body, that ſo he may apply ſomewhat unto thee for thy health and cure, ſo muſt thou doe: I ſay, in the ſickneſſe of thy ſoule, then thou muſt flie and ſeeke to Gods Miniſter; for the Prieſts lips ought to preſerve knowledge, and thou muſt ſeeke the Law at his mouth, ſaith the Lord by his Prophet, Mal. 2.7. To him then thou muſt open the wounds of thy ſoule, and all the cauſes and occaſions of thy feare; whether they be thy ſinnes (if any trouble thy conſcience) or thy temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to ſinnes, thy weakeneſſes of faith and holineſſe, or the like; ſo that hee upon view and ſight of thy eſtate, and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of thy faith and repentance (though they be but weake) may apply the promiſes of mercy, the comfortable refreſhing Oyle of the Goſpel unto thy ſoule: But yet heerein alſo heede and warineſſe muſt be taken, to what Miniſter, and to what
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117878:13"/>ſpirituall Father we doe repoſe and put our truſt and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in for this ſo great a buſineſſe; for we muſt not ſend to the Schiſmaticall Anabaptiſt, Browniſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who preacheth and applieth all judgements, and little or no mercy; for, then he may make the wound worſe then it is; but in this caſe, ſend to the godly reformed Miniſter, not to ſome up-ſtart, Trades-man, or body Miniſter, of which at this day are too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; but know this, that our life is hid with Chriſt in God, Col. 3.3. For, as Trees in the cold and ſtormy Winter, ſo good men and women in tempeſts and anguiſhes of ſoule, ſeem to be dead, not onely to the world, but even to themſelves. Whence note, that Acts 20.9.10. <hi>Eutichus</hi> there is an Emblem of a Chriſtian in temptation; for, he fell from an high loft, and was taken up dead, and ſo was reputed of all that ware preſent; but (ſaith the Text) the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> laid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe upon him, and imbraced him, and ſo found life in him, and ſet him on his legs; ſo though a man fall high, from heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grace, even to the very pit of hell, if it were poſſible, yet he may be raiſed againe by ſome skilfull and painefull <hi>Paul,</hi> by applying the comforts of the Goſpel, and ſo rightly ſhewing him that his life is not altogether extinguiſhed and put out, but hid onely in Chriſt, and that the ſame is to be found againe in God.</p>
            <p>But for thoſe that thinke (if there be any ſuch) that any man may as well abſolve or baptize, or uſe any other Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Function or Office in the Church (but ſome, if not too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, could be contented that there were no Churches) as well as the Miniſters of God, who onely are lawfully called thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, I would have ſuch to know, that he that ſent forth to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, Mark. 16.16. he ſent alſo to remit ſinnes, ſaying, as my Father ſent me, ſo ſend I you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> John 20.12.13. As there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore none can or ought to baptize, though he uſe the ſame wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117878:14"/>and words, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. and 10. verſ. but onely, the lawfull Miniſter, Heb. 5.4. I ſay, he onely which Chriſt hath called and authorized to this Divine and Miniſteriall Function: So though others (I confeſſe) may comfort with good words; yet none can abſolve from ſinne, but onely Chriſt, and thoſe to whom Chriſt hath committed the holy Miniſtery and words of reconciliation, 2. Cor. 5.18.19. and of their abſolving Chriſt ſpeakes, in Luk. 10.16. He that heareth you heareth me: In a doubtfull title, thou wilt aske the counſell and advice of ſome skilfull Lawyer; in perrill of ſickneſſe, thou wilt enquire of the learned Phiſitian; and is there no danger in the dread, and feare of damnation, for a ſinner to be his owne Judge? Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious <hi>Calvin</hi> teacheth this point of Doctrine moſt plainely, <hi>Et ſi omnes mutuo nos debeamus conſolari, &amp;c.</hi> Although (ſaith he) we ought to comfort and confirme one another in the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Gods mercy; yet we ſee that the Miniſters are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, as Witneſſes and Sureties to aſcertaine our conſciences of the remiſſion of ſinnes: Inſomuch, as they are ſaid to remit ſinnes, and to looſe ſoules, <hi>&amp;c. Beza</hi> highly commendeth this practice; and <hi>Luther</hi> ſaith, that he had rather loſe a thouſand worlds, then ſuffer private confeſſions to be, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And our Church hath ever moſt ſoundly admitted and maintained the truth of this Doctrine; and heerein I might bring in the viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſick in our Liturgy, but that is now aboliſhed, and for my owne part, I never was againſt the aboliſhing of it; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this I ſay, and ſay of it, if thoſe in Authority had puniſhed ſome of thoſe that rent it out of the Churches, before that Authority had made the ſame of no validity and uſe, that then it would have made ſome (and that a great many too) have leaned more freely to them and their Authority, who now (I feare) ſtand but as neuters; and the not puniſhing of ſuch, hath been a great cauſe of the augmentation and encreaſing of this
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117878:14"/>civill uncivill and unnaturall Warre: There was once much wondering when the Pope fell heere in this Kingdome, as now they wonder to ſee the Prelates caſt downe, and ſo the world did once wonder to ſee the Maſſe caſt away and diſliked, and now many wonder to thinke that the Lithurgy ſhould be ſo ſwept away. And for my part, I pray God grant that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple doe not at laſt take a ſurfeit of that moſt Divine Ordinance of preaching, for no violent thing laſts long: Well, but we all complaine of our preſent miſery, by the unhappy and bloody diſtractions of the Kingdome, by this inbred and unnaturall Warre: But yet few conſider ſeriouſly or the cauſe, whence they come; for information heerein, take and obſerve this, that ſinne is the onely cauſe of every affliction, and of all puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whether to private men, or whole Kingdomes, Eſay. 26.9. We by our ſinnes have provoked God to anger, and God ſhewes his anger by theſe judgements upon the whole Nation, Deut. 6.15. King and Subjects have ſinned, and now King and Subjects are puniſhed, Deut. 28.63. Nay, God cauſeth us to puniſh one another; and he doth it either to reforme us, or elſe to deſtroy us. But (I dare ſay) God is the efficient cauſe of all: Yea, the cauſe of all cauſes; all other cauſes are but Gods inſtruments; now the inſtrumentall cauſe of theſe our diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, are wicked men, 2. Chron. 22.2.3. God uſeth one ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to puniſh another, as <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſinnes were puniſhed by wicked <hi>Shiſhake,</hi> and by idolatrous <hi>Aſher,</hi> Eſay. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.5. whom God cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the rod of his anger, and the ſtaffe of his hand, 2. Sam. 12.11.12.13. So God puniſhed <hi>Davids</hi> ſinne by wicked <hi>Abſolon,</hi> and King <hi>Rehobcams</hi> ſinne by his rebellious people, 2. King. 14.16. and the ſinne of the people by their King <hi>Jeroboam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet though God do uſe wicked men for his inſtruments, yet wicked men doe but wickedly, even in the things wherein God uſeth them; for naturally ſtill they are but the Divels in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117878:15"/>to execute his will, and their owne Diveliſh malice: as ye may ſee Job 1.15. But to paſſe and goe where wee were, for Abſolution, wee finde that Doctor <hi>Holland</hi> abſolved Doctor <hi>Reynolds</hi> at his death, who not being able to ſpeake, yet he kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the hands wherewith he was abſolved. And ſo King <hi>James,</hi> of bleſſed memory, as I have credibly heard, when hee lay on his death bed, ſent for a Reverend Biſhop to come and give him his Abſolution. But yet I ſay further, and that moſt juſtly and truly to, that our Church hath aboliſhed, as it was very fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, the Tyrannous and Antichriſtian abuſe of Popiſh Auricu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Confeſſion, which they very fondly thruſt upon the ſouls of Chriſtians, as an expiatory ſacrifice, and a meritorious ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for ſinne, racking their conſciences to confeſſe when they feele or felt no diſtreſſe, and to enumerate all their ſinnes, which is impoſſible; that ſo by this meanes they might dive into the ſecrets of men and women, which many times proved pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and hurtfull, not only to private perſons, but alſo to publick States.</p>
            <p>But to leave the Church of Rome to their fopperies, let all good Chriſtians be admoniſhed to beware of their owne natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall corruptions, which is a thing that is by nature in the beſt; for all are, in this point, borne Papiſts, and there is no man that hath not, as <hi>Luther</hi> ſayd, a Pope in his belly, a high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit and opinion of his owne workes, (whereby we thinke wee tie God unto us) and yet I dare ſay, there is in us no reall ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, no true ſubſtance. For wee can of right chalenge nothing at Gods hands, be our workes never ſo good or excellent: for before thy converſion what canſt thou deſerve, when every of thy workes and actions, are but as ſo many ſinnes? for to the impure, all things are impure, Tit. 1.15. And without fayth it is impoſſible to pleaſe God, Heb. 11.6. And alſo after conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, all thy workes are tainted with ſin, whereas if they could
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117878:15"/>merit or deferve, then they muſt be abſolutely good and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous. Oh then chalenge nothing for thy works ſake, for thou mayſt know their imperfections, and in begging any bleſſing from above, from whence commeth every good and perfect gift, Ja. 1.17. I ſay, therein uſe no other plea, but the freedome of Gods grace: Let Papiſts lay claym unto them, as they are ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, but let us claym them as we are ſonnes. For know, it is not <hi>Eſaus</hi> riches, nor <hi>Jeſables</hi> birth, nor <hi>Goliahs</hi> ſtrength, nor <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitophels</hi> wit, nor <hi>Abſolons</hi> beauty, nor <hi>Sauls</hi> ſtature, nor <hi>Dives</hi> fine Purple, nor the Fooles great Barnes, that can aſſure or certifie the ſoule of the favour of God: for, I dare ſay, all theſe a man may have, and yet bee of old ordayned for condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But as wee were, I ſay, thou muſt confeſſe thy ſinnes and weakneſſes, (as the Reverend Divine Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> in his Caſe of Conſcience, obſerveth) That ſo the Miniſter of God may pronounce the ſentence of Abſolution (of thy free remiſſion and reconciliation with God in Chriſt) unto thee: for, as is ſhewed a little before, the Miniſter hath the Keyes committed unto him for that end, Joh. 20, 22.23. and that hence thy hope and confidence in God may be confirmed, which the Miniſter may truly doe, if by thy confeſſion, he finds in thee, the grounds and ſignes of fayth and repentance; and heere, in this ſmall Tract, I doubt not, but fully hope, that I have not ſpent my time in vaine, but that ſome, if not all, that ſhall ſee and read it, ſhall finde ſome comfort thereby unto their ſoules, (if thou be called, and brought to repentance and fayth in Chriſt) deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre not. I will heere againe put you in minde of one ground of comfort more, for, or in ſtead of many, and it is this: That a deſire to repent and beleeve, in a touched heart and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, is fayth and repentance it ſelfe; for God accepteth the will for the deed, as I ſayd before, though it bee not ſo in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet in Gods acceptation by and in Chriſt it is ſo. And this
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117878:16"/>is evident in the holy Scriptures; firſt, becauſe if there bee a willing mind, it is accepted, not according to that a man hath not, but according to that he hath, 2. Cor. 8.12. And doth not God only call all, that thirſt and deſire the waters of life, yea, and offers thereof freely, Eſa. 55.1.2. I ſay, if they doe but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and thirſt for it, hee then promiſeth to give it them freely, Revel. 21.6. and 22.17. And he will be as good as his word to us, becauſe his word and promiſe is to us Yea, and Amen, 2. Cor. 1.20. Seeing it is thus with the Lord, that thou ſhalt be ſure to receive and taſte of theſe waters of comfort, if thou wilt pray for it, and expect with patience, and tarry the Lords leaſure for it, then thou art and ſhalt be bleſſed in the deſire of it; for, Bleſſed are they that hunger and thirſt after righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; for, firſt or laſt, they ſhall bee ſatisfied, Mat. 5.6. And then bleſſed ſhalt thou bee in the happy poſſeſſion of it; hope well: for if it were not for hope, as it is in the Proverbe, Heart would breake; and pray heartily for it: for, I dare ſay, Prayer is an excellent Antidote againſt any deſpayre, temptation, or aſſault whatſoever; and no Prayer comparable to Chriſts, which he hath taught us, Mat. 6. But in a word for concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, know, Chriſtian and loving Reader, and deſpayre not. For Chriſt is the doore to Heaven, Faith is the locke of this doore, and Prayer is the key to open this locke; which may bee a great motive to keepe a man from deſpayre, and therefore not to be diſtracted for theſe times, though troubled with an unnaturall warre: but in a word let me adviſe thee, often, and with zeale and fervency of ſpirit, to turne this Key, Prayer; for as the body cannot live without the ſoule, no more can the ſoule live without Prayer. But for thy further ſatisfaction heerein, I referre thee to a Sermon of mine, entituled, <hi>The great Eſtimate that redounds by Croſſes and Afflictions.</hi> The Text
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117878:16"/>being but one word, <hi>viz.</hi> Rom. 8.18. the word <hi>Afflictions:</hi> as alſo to my Expoſition on the Lords Prayer. Thus (bleſſed ſoule) thou haſt for thy comfort, <hi>A Hand-kercheffe,</hi> to wipe away all dolour and griefe, or what may trouble thy ſoule or conſcience for the miſeries or calamities of the Times, and a Directory to all happineſſe. To which God in his good time bring thee. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
